I'm going to warn you that the
information contained in this video is
not going to wow you with new habits,
foods, or otherwise that you haven't
heard before. But what it will do is
open your eyes to how little you have to
change in your day-to-day life to
achieve huge leaps in your own life
expectancy. Not only that, but huge
leaps in your quality of life as well.
All of that due to three habit changes.
There's this study and if you read the
title you'll note that it speaks to
three fundamental aspects of health. If
you want consider them like three
infinity stones that belong to the
infinity glove of power. In the Marvel
universe there are six and in the health
science universe there are three at
least for the time being. The six are
power, time, reality, soul, mind, and
space. Now if you don't follow Marvel,
don't worry about it. Let's just say
that each stone is incredibly powerful
in its own way. And once it's added to
the Infinity Glove, the powers combine
into a superpower. Now, in the health
science universe, unlike the Marvel
universe, the stones read, "Physical
activity, nutrition, and sleep.
Controlling these three stones will
extend your life forever."
Okay, maybe not forever, but it'll make
a big difference as I'll show you in a
minute. But even more impressive, what
happens when we just nudge them a little
bit. Five minutes more of one, two
minutes more of another, and half a
serving of the final one. We'll get to
that. This study involved around 60,000
participants that were tracked over
eight years to identify the risk of
death at varying levels of shall we say
commitment to the three pillars that we
just discussed. This was quantified as a
span score which stands for are you
ready for this?
Sleep, physical activity and nutrition
score. SPAN brilliant. So in combination
there's a relatively linear relationship
between span score and lifespan
improvements. The left side shows added
years of life and the horizontal axis
indicates the increase in span score.
That's a good thing. Clearly higher span
score relates to increased lifespan up
to about 11 or 12 years added. The same
was true when looking at health span as
well. That was defined as being
diseasefree. Now again, higher span
score related to greater odds of being
disease-free for longer. The main point
here is that if you work on these three
pillars of health, physical activity,
nutrition, and sleep, you are predicted
to improve your lifespan and health span
by years, even as much as a decade or
longer. Now, I'm surprised by you. I
really thought that if I sat here and
told you the most obvious thing in the
world, you'd be blown away. Huh? I
really underestimated you. Okay. Okay.
Joking aside, what are these numbers? 5
minutes, 2 minutes, and half a serving.
There is an assumption of doing poorly
in all three categories puts you in the
bottom fifth percentile of each. Only
sleeping 5 and 1/2 hours, only getting 7
minutes of physical activity per day,
and a low diet quality score of 37. Now,
if you increase your sleep by five
minutes, add in two more minutes of
physical activity, and increase your
diet quality score by five points, which
amounts for half a serving more of
vegetables or 1 and a half servings of
grains. The estimated longevity effect
is a 1year gain. Now, several things to
say here. Some of which I feel I need to
stipulate every time before my head is
forfeit to the end of a spear like the
Orurukai after the Roherim rode them
down on the outskirts of Fangorn forest.
People will oftent times feel pretty
zesty about that last one, nutrition.
I'd like to point out that if you're on
a more specialized nutrition like a
vegan diet or a ketogenic diet and so
on, these results will not apply to you
onetoone because none of the data was
based on individuals following those
diet patterns. Those small changes that
we just went over are for the extremes
in the lack of healthy nutrition. Those
consuming almost all the unhealthy
ultrarocessed foods with little whole
foods. So, taking that comparison,
the worse nutrition, the bottom 5%, and
making subtle changes like the inclusion
of a little more vegetables or grains,
plus the numbers that we went over for
sleep and physical activity yields this
one-year added life relationship. Then,
from that initial improvement, small
improvements yield more and more life
extension. Again, relative to that
bottom 5% in all those categories. Of
course, if you already do some of these
things, you can already factor in
several years of added life extension
simply because you are already not in
the bottom 5%. Now, let's discuss what
it takes to have a 10 or more year life
extension. to raise your span score to a
point of 10 years or more added life
plus some improvements in health span.
Additional sleep from 5 and a half hours
was marked at an additional 3 hours of
sleep. So a total of about 8 hours 8 and
1/2 hours plus an additional 25 minutes
of physical activity and a 35 point
improvement in dietary quality score.
for that level of dietary improvement.
According to the study, it would amount
to three or more servings of fruit,
three or more servings of vegetables,
three or more servings of whole grains,
and cutting sugary drinks to a minimum.
That would create an ideal consumption
across those categories. There are other
ways of getting to that level of
improvement. However, that's just one
example. Obviously, I can't detail every
possible scenario and it probably
doesn't matter because of what we'll
discuss next. But the bottom line is
that even a few minutes improvement in
physical activity and sleep and small
dietary changes can have outsiz impact
on longevity and reaching greater levels
of each has tremendous impact on
longevity. Now, as I alluded, your diet
may not matter as much, and that's
because one of the other two has
significantly more impact on your
longevity than the other two. Can you
guess which? Is it sleep or is it
physical activity?
As you think about it, let me briefly
mention that there's also estimates on
life extension. If you are able to
improve one or two of these pillars of
health and keep the last one in a bad
spot and what is the minimum effort to
achieve the best mortality risk
reduction across all three health
pillars and more. I'm covering that in
the extended version of this video that
you're watching, which also comes with a
full article, a one paragraph summary of
the most important factors. And oh yeah,
you get access to all these perks right
over here, like live sessions with me, a
private podcast going over the month's
investigations, a private email list,
and more. It's the full access to all my
work, the Physionic Insiders. Link to
check it out is in the description.
Okay, got your guess? If you guessed
physical activity,
you are correct. Woohoo.
We can see that here. Life expectancy is
on the vertical axis again and each
condition is on the horizontal. Sleep,
physical activity, and diet quality. The
higher the lines go, the better. You'll
notice that sleep and physical activity
have huge effects, but diet quality does
not. I'll explain why that is in a
minute. But I'd also quick point out
that the values here are slightly
different than what we went over before.
For example, the ideal sleep was around
7.5 hours, not 8.5 hours. The reason for
that is because of how the data was
analyzed. Initially, we were looking at
them in combination, yet here we're
looking at them in isolation. But why
would nutrition have such a feeble
relationship with longevity? Well,
generally it doesn't. But the
researchers were looking at nutrition
independent of calorie consumption and
weight. These two factors play a massive
role on our health. But the researchers
were asking a different question than
usual. They were asking about the impact
of nutrition components, so independent
of weight loss and weight gain and their
impact. In addition, the 60,000
participants that volunteered were part
of a well-known data set called the UK
Bioank, which even the researchers
acknowledge has a healthy volunteer
bias, meaning that the data set is
already healthier than usual. There were
some additional explanations like
regression, delilution bias and others,
but that's getting into some technical
fairyland that we rarely wander. The big
point here is that yes, physical
activity is the primary driver of
longevity, then sleep, and then
nutrition. But nutrition's impact is
likely subdued and probably has more
impact than what we're seeing here. Now,
I realize I've thrown a lot a bunch of
numbers around at you, and it's not an
easy study to wrap your head around. I
was actually trying to understand the
distinction between these analyses
myself for a while. And truth be told,
there are weaknesses to the study, like
the fact that they only measured sleep,
nutrition, and and physical activity
once. An inherent issue of these kinds
of studies, or the healthy volunteer
bias, or eliminating one of the causal
benefits of nutrition, weight. Still, in
broad strokes, we can take away two
things. One, doing small amounts, even a
few minutes of improvements in sleep and
physical activity can have tremendous
returns, far more than what might be
expected since we're talking about years
of extra life for a few minutes of
input. And two, broad strokes. The ideal
targets are to sleep 7.5 to eight hours
per night. Average 50 to 75 minutes of
moderate to vigorous physical activity.
That means like brisk walks, uh, cycling
or anything that gets your you at least
a little out of breath. And finally,
keeping in mind that the limitations,
high vegetable, whole grain, and fruit
intake, that is predicted to yield a
decade of extra life and better quality
life, too, than if you were to do none
of those things. Some of that might seem
obvious, some of it may be new. But even
if it isn't novel to you, consider it a
further reminder that the basics, the
pillars, the three stones of health, of
power should always be the focus. And
because physical activity was so potent,
there's another study that I covered
that discussed how you can manipulate
physical activity and cram it into just
a minute or two and create immense
mortality protective effects for
yourself. I also make a bit of a fool of
myself. Just click here. Thanks for
tuning in. It's always appreciated. See
you in the next one. See you.